<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../../../config/concept.xsl"?>
<docnavy-etm>
    <front>
        <docno></docno>
        <fsection></fsection>
    </front>
    <body>
        <chapter>
            <title>Early Underwater Devices</title>
            <section>
                <subsection>
                    <title>1A1. Early Greek devices.</title>
                    <para0>
                        <para>The submarine first became a major factor in naval warfare during World War I, when Germany demonstrated its full potentialities. However, its advent at that time, marked by wholesale sinkings of Allied shipping, was in reality the culmination of a long process of development.</para>
                        <para>Ancient history includes occasional records of attempts at underwater operations in warfare. The Athenians are said to have used divers to clear the entrance of the harbor of Syracuse during the siege of that city; during his operations against Tyre, Alexander the Great ordered divers to impede or destroy any submarine defenses the city might undertake to build. But in none of these records is there a direct reference to the use of submersible apparatus of any kind. There is, however, a legend that Alexander the Great himself made a descent into the sea in a device which kept its occupants dry and admitted light.</para>
                        <para>In the Middle Ages, the Arabian historian Boha-Eddin reports that a diver using submersible apparatus succeeded in gaining entrance into Ptolemais (Acre) during the siege of that city in A.D. 1150. And in 1538, a diving bell was built and tested at Toledo, Spain. Although it attracted the attention of the Emperor Charles V, the device was never further developed and passed quickly into oblivion.</para>
                    </para0>                   
                </subsection>
                <subsection>
                    <title>1A2. Bourne's idea.</title>
                    <para0>
                        <para>Not until 1580 does any record appear of a craft designed to be navigated under water. In that year, William Bourne, a British naval officer, made designs of a completely enclosed boat which could be submerged and rowed under the surface. The device consisted of a wooden framework covered with waterproofed leather. It was to be submerged by reducing its volume as a result of contracting the sides through the use of hand vises. Although Bourne never built this boat, a similar construction sponsored by one Magnus Pegelius was launched in 1605. But the designers made one serious oversight. They failed to consider the tenacity of underwater mud, and the craft was buried at the bottom of a river during initial underwater trials.</para>
                    </para0>                   
                </subsection>
                <subsection>
                    <title>1A3. Van Drebel's submersible.</title>
                    <para0>
                        <para>It is to Cornelius Van Drebel, a Dutch physician, that credit is usually given for building the first submarine. To him is conceded the honor of successfully maneuvering his craft, during repeated trials in the Thames River, at depths of 12 and 15 feet beneath the surface.</para>
                        <para>Van Drebel's craft resembled those of Bourne and Pegelius in that its outer hull consisted of greased leather over a wooden framework. Oars, extending through the sides and sealed with tight-fitting leather flaps, provided propulsion either on the surface or when submerged. Van Drebel built his first boat in 1620 and followed it later with two others both larger but embodying the same principles. It is reported that after repeated tests, James I took a trip in one of the larger models and demonstrated its safety. But despite this evidence of royal favor, the craft failed to arouse the interest of the navy in an age when all conception of the possibilities of submarine warfare was still far in the future.</para>
                    </para0>                   
                </subsection>
                <subsection>
                    <title>1A4. Eighteenth century plans.</title>
                    <para0>
                        <para>Submarine boats seem to have been numerous in the early years of the 18th century. By 1727 no fewer than 14 types had been patented in England alone.</para>
                        <para>An unidentified inventor whose work is described in the Gentleman's Magazine for 1747 introduced an ingenious device for submerging and surfacing his submarine. His craft was to have had a number of goatskins built into the hull, each of which was to be connected to an aperture in the bottom. He planned to submerge the vessel by filling the skins with water, and to bring it to the surface again by forcing the water out of the skins with a "twisting rod." This seems to have been the first approach to the modern ballast tank. By that time, ideas were plentiful, some of them fanciful and grotesque, but some containing elements capable of practical application. Lack of full understanding of the physical and mechanical principles involved, coupled with the well-nigh universal conviction that underwater navigation was impossible and of no practical value, postponed for more than another hundred years the attempt to utilize a submarine in warfare.</para>
                    </para0>                   
                </subsection>
            </section>
        </chapter>
    </body>
</docnavy-etm>